Guide to the James Rogers Papers, 1768-1794 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Rogers papers 1768-1794 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rogers, James, d. 1799.
10 linear feet Extent: Approximately 28,000 Items
James Rogers was a merchant from Bristol, England, a ship owner, and a slave trader who engaged in various types of trade in Newfoundland, the American colonies, the West Indies, Ireland, Africa, Spain, Portugal, and elsewhere. Collection consists of photocopies of documents originally belonging to James Rogers, Bristol, England, a merchant, ship owner, and slave trader. The material, dating from 1768-1794, largely consists of incoming correspondence, bills of sale, receipts, and other items related to ships' voyages and trading activities. Many of these voyages were for the purpose of acquiring and trading slaves from Africa. A paper guide to the collection created by the donor of the collection and available to researchers includes descriptions of most of the ships' voyages.
rogersjames
Language: Material inEnglish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Rogers Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1967.
Biographical Note
James Rogers was a merchant from Bristol, England, a ship owner, and a slave trader who engaged in various types of trade in Newfoundland, the American colonies, the West Indies, Ireland, Africa, Spain, Portugal, and elsewhere.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of copies of documents originally belonging to James Rogers, Bristol, England merchant and ship owner. The material, dating from 1768 to 1794, largely consists of incoming correspondence, bills of sale, receipts, and other items related to ships' voyages and trading activities. The papers are arranged into three series: Ships' Voyages; Bills; and Business Papers and Letters. Much of the material in the collection concerns the African slave trade, but there is also information on the cotton, sugar, and fishing markets and trade. Documentation includes accounts for materials supplied to ships in which Rogers had an interest; accounts of ships, cargoes, and insurance; receipts for advances of wages to ships' crews; bills of exchange; petitions from Rogers' creditors; statements of shares in cargoes and ships; letters from ships' captains in Africa relating to purchases; comments on the state of the market; price information; letters from agents overseas; and other materials. One set of documents about the Mermaid contains comments on a slave insurrection on board. The collection also includes the same documents on twenty reels of microfilm, but the arrangement of the paper copies by topic and by date renders them easier to use. The original documents became the property of the Public Record Office, London, as exhibits in litigation that followed Rogers' declaration of bankruptcy in 1793, and are currently held in the Court of Bankruptcy records, indexed as B 3/4177 and B 3/4185, in the National Archives in Kew, England.
The folders in the Ships' Voyages Series are organized alphabetically by ship name, then within chronologically, with correspondence regarding the voyage first, followed by bills and other related items. The items in the Bills Series are arranged chronologically. The Business Papers and Letters are organized into two main subgroupings: by country of trade, and by name of correspondent; there are also smaller groups of miscellaneous correspondence, including Rogers' bankruptcy papers, which contain information on how the slave trade was set up, and on speculations in the cotton market.
Place-names mentioned in these papers include: Green Island, N.Y.; Kennebec, Maine; many coastal towns in Newfoundland; Cove Island, Ontario; Belize; many locations in the Caribbean Islands; and coastal cities in England, Ireland, Portugal (including the Azores Islands), and Spain (including the Canary and Balearic Islands).
A ninety-page paper guide to the collection created by the donor of the collection and available to the researcher includes descriptions of most of the ships' voyages.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bankruptcy -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Colonies -- History; Great Britain -- Commerce -- History; Merchants -- England -- Bristol -- Correspondence; Microfilm; Rogers, James, d. 1799; Rogers, Joseph; Shipping -- Great Britain; Slave trade -- Africa -- History; Slave trade -- Atlantic Ocean Region -- History; Slave trade -- Great Britain -- History; Slave trade -- Caribbean Area -- History; Slave traders -- England
Related Material
Court of Bankruptcy Records, B 3/4177 and B 3/4185
National Archives, Kew, England
Contents of Collection
- Ships' Voyages Series, 1760s-1790s, (18 boxes)
  Arranged by destination, then within by subcategories of major voyages, minor voyages, and miscellaneous or multiple voyages. Documents arranged alphabetically by name of ship, then chronologically, with correspondence first, then bills and other papers following.
  - Voyage to Africa/West Indies
    Arranged by major, minor, and multiple voyages, and within alhpabetically by ship's name. Documents pertaining to the voyages include bills, cargo accounts, receipts, and correspondence from ships' captains. A ninety-page document researched and created by the donor of the Rogers Papers, and available in the library, briefly describes the voyage (route, cargo, and other details) of almost all the ships.
    - Major voyages
      - African Queen (Box 1)
      - Bristol
      - Commerce
      - Commerce (Box 2)
      - Crescent
      - Daniel (Box 3)
      - Diana
      - Dragon (Box 4)
      - Fame
      - Fanny (Box 5)
      - Flora
      - Fly (Box 6)
      - Friendship
      - James (Box 7)
      - Jupiter
      - Lyon
      - Martin
      - Martin (Box 8)
      - Minerva
      - Monmouth (Box 9)
      - Morning Star
      - Pearle
      - Pearle (Box 10)
      - Rodney
      - Rodney (Box 11)
      - Ruby
      - Sarah
      - Sarah (Box 12)
      - William and Mary
    - Minor voyages
      - Cape Coast (Box 12)
      - Experiment
      - Harmony
      - Gibson
      - Jamaica Planter (Box 13)
      - Langrishe
      - Mervin
      - Nancy
      - Princess
      - Recovery
      - Swit
      - Thetis
      - Trelawney
      - Trelawney (Box 14)
      - Triton
      - Tuba
      - Young Crescent
    - Miscellaneous voyages
      Arranged alphabetically, and then chronologically if enough material is present.
      - Albion-Britannica (Box 14)
      - Brothers-Caplin
      - Chance-Hope (Box 15)
      - Hornet-Lydia
      - M-Mercury
      - Mermaid folders: includes documents describing slave insurrection on board the Mermaid
      - Milford-Pilot
      - Plato-Roman Eagle
      - Russia-York
    - Multiple voyages
      Groups of papers which concern more than one ship's voyage to Africa, and or the West Indies. Arranged alphabetically by name on top of photocopy page.
      - Multiple voyages (Box 16)
  - Voyages to Newfoundland
    Contains material documenting ships' trading activities in Newfoundland. Arranged in three groupings: major, minor, and other various voyages.
    - Major, minor, and miscellaneous voyages to Newfoundland (Box 17-18)
      Major voyages: Betsey, Centurion, Industry, and Richard. Minor voyages: Chepstow, Denizen, Elizabeth, Sacra Famiglia, and the Swallow. Miscellaneous voyages arranged alphabetically, and then chronologically if enough material is present.
- Bills Series, 1774-1793, (2 boxes)
  Arranged in chronological order, followed by several groupings of bills related to specific firms, then bills related to Newfoundland trade.
  - 1774-1789, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1790-1793 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Cox and Hallett; Willaim Cross; James Cross; George Alexander Clibborn
  - Robinson and Heywood; C. Jones; James Rogers, Parry and Ludlam
  - Newfoundland bills, 1774-1792
- Business and Trading Letters, 1768-1794 and undated, (5 boxes)
  Arranged in two major subgroupings: by country of origin and by individual correspondents. These are followed by sections for other various letters and papers, including four folders related to Rogers' bankruptcy in March 1793.
  - Trading firm letters, African trade, 1777-1794 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Trading firm letters, Newfoundland trade, 1782-1792
  - Newfoundland trade business letters
    - Stephen Hunt, 1784 July-1788 Dec. (on fish trade and prices) (Box 20)
    - Thomas Lewis, 1783 Nov.-1790 June
    - Joseph Rogers, 1777 Sept.-1778 Dec. (brother of James)
  - Other business letters and papers
    - Richard Fydell, 1778 Oct.-1792 May (from Bath and Chepstow) (Box 20)
    - William Grumly, 1785 Dec.-1793 June (from Tortola on the sugar market) (Box 21)
    - Joseph Rogers, 1781 May-1790 June (from St. Croix and Tortola, on islands and on sugar market)
    - Joseph Daltera, 1781 July-1790 Sept. (on sugar, rum, and other markets in Liverpool)
    - Other business letters, 1777 May-1792 Feb.
    - Other business letters, 1777 May-1792 Feb. (Box 22)
    - Clibborn's Underwriting Books, 1768-1775, (2 folders)
    - Rogers' bankruptcy papers, (2 folders)
    - Rogers' bankruptcy papers, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous unarranged letters and papers, (3 folders)
    - Miscellaneous unarranged letters and papers, (3 folders) (Box 24)